I'm Heston Blumenthal and for the last eight weeks I've been perfecting eight classic dishes, but now I attempt to take on what, for many people, is the biggest menu of the year - Christmas dinner.
This is the big one, the meal we all look forward to, and I'm going to stop at nothing to get it right.
This is my chance to incorporate all of my Christmas memories into one glorious meal.
My restaurant has three Michelin stars and has been voted one of the best in the world and now I'm going to bring my multi-sensory approach to cooking to deliver a once-in-a-lifetime Christmas meal, unlike anything ever seen.
'I'll be visiting Santa's little helper to try and make reindeer-milk ice cream.'
I can't see the teat.
'I lovingly rear two special geese to capture a tradition of Christmas past.'
'And I'll be travelling to the Middle East in the footsteps of the Three Wise Men 'to create a dish from gold, frankincense and myrrh.'
It's not just the meal that's going to be special.
I'm also going to create a Christmas dining room that's out of this world to give my diners a Christmas experience like no other.
Christmas wouldn't be Christmas without friends, so I've invited six special guests to enjoy this magical meal and they've no idea what I've got in store for them.
'This is my perfect Christmas dinner.'
If you asked people to name three...
Five of the most memorable meals they've ever had, the food will be good, but most of the time it will be the setting, the company, the occasion.
There will be other things - the environment provides those sensory triggers, the memories, that make it so wonderful.
'First on the agenda was creating the perfect setting for my meal.
'My idea was to turn a local car park into an incredible Christmas dining room.'
A stone entrance.
The guests will come in through here and then they walk into what is basically a drawing room.
One of the panels will actually be a false wall.
This is a forest of Christmas trees.
The table will be there, and the chandelier.
Sounds good.
A gloves-off Christmas dinner.
So, with my dining room ready, it was time for my guests to arrive.
I've invited six special guests, who all love their food, to come and share this feast.
I'm looking forward to it enormously.
We wouldn't be here if we weren't, but Heston is probably the most exciting chef in Britain, if not the world.
It's this thing with snail porridge and things that taste different and steam and nitrogen and gas, and all that stuff.
I know somebody who's been here, and had seafood and they put... headphones on you and you had the sound of the sea.
I think we'll be wearing goblin hats.
It'll be something stupid - you'll put the food in your mouth and go, "This has no taste!"
Then he'll stand behind you and shake your head violently and then you go, "Oh, yes, I get it now.
Bergamot!"
You know, the satsuma bomb goes off!
Exactly.
The drawing room on this set was the opportunity for me to generate some excitement.
Oh!
Please help yourself, come in.
Don't do this at home!
We actually made what looked like glass Christmas tree decorations and filled it with salmon mousse, but it wasn't glass.
It's very good.
Salmon in a light bulb!
That's extraordinary.
Next for my guests was the very traditional Christmas treat of mulled wine, but with a little extra magic.
Oh, my God!
Almost right down the middle, one half is hot and the other half is cold.
If I can just...
How do you do that?!
How have they halved it?
Half of it is hot and half of it is quite cold.
Exactly.
One half of your mouth is frozen while the other is warm.
It took me a very long time to develop that to the level where I thought it was good enough to serve, but I can't disclose the secret because it would lose the magic.
I don't think I've ever drunk anything quite so ridiculous in my life!
Now it's a mandarin mousse - egg white, vodka and mandarin - that when poached in liquid nitrogen becomes a meringue-like taste explosion.
It's been dusted with dried mandarin powder and then there's a little spritz, a little spray of thyme oil in the air and if you get the whole thing in your mouth in one go, you get two jets of vapour coming out of your nostrils, like a dragon!
There's steam coming out of your nose.
THEY LAUGH Like a bull!
Oh, my God, that was amazing.
Six veteran media types and we're all reduced to eight-year-old children.
Which was exactly the effect I wanted to create.
Then, through a secret panel, it was time to reveal my Christmas dining room.
Look at the snow!
It's Narnia!
A first for some.
It's so beautiful.
It was like entering some kind of winter wonderland.
Um...it just looked glorious.
Oh, look at that.
Stunning.
You walk through this... entrance hall that's been created into this outdoor...
Disneyland of Christmas-ness!
Oh, look at this!
If this is the amount of work they put into the trees, what the hell is the food going to taste like?
So to the meal and my first course.
And there's three things that are key to that.
Gold, frankincense and myrrh, which took me to Oman.
I'd come to the Middle East on the trail of the Three Wise Men.
My ambition was to track down 2,000-year-old frankincense from the time of Christ and include it in my meal.
To do this, I had to travel to the place where the Wise Men themselves might have found it.
A legendary frankincense trading post - the lost city of Ubar.
This is satellite imagery from the late '80s, which led to the discovery of the lost city of Ubar.
The thing that really enabled the archaeologists to find this city was these - these camel tracks, and where they meet, this triangle, that was Ubar.
And we believe this is where the Three Wise Men would have actually passed through.
Now, these camel tracks have turned into a kind of road and we're on one.
And I can't believe it!
There's a camel.
At least we knew we were on the right route.
A few miles down the road, we found Ubar and one of the men responsible for its discovery - archaeologist Yuri Zarins.
The site itself probably goes back to 200-300 BC, but the actual occupation goes back to 5,000 BC.
People have been here for the last 7,000 years.
Biblical research has shown that the Wise Men came from parts of Saudi Arabia.
They did bring frankincense and myrrh to the baby Jesus.
That road would've come through here, straight up to the Levantine coast.
We can see the outline of the town itself, the main settlement.
Merchants were attached to each one of these.
They'd be selling goods - frankincense and myrrh etc. So we're in a market stall?
It's a market stall.
That's exactly what it is.
'At this site, they have excavated biblical frankincense, 'but, sadly, it was far too valuable and rare for me to use in a meal.
'Instead, I was going to have to find and harvest my own.'
Is there anywhere relatively near here I can actually tap into a frankincense tree?
Across the river.
It's only 50km to where the frankincense trees grow.
This is when they start to harvest, at the end of the monsoon season.
Frankincense was, and is, used for a myriad of purposes, from burning at funerals to medicine.
In ancient times, this crystallised tree sap was one of the most expensive things on earth and would have been brought by the Wise Men as a highly symbolic gift.
Finally, my quest led me to the harvesting fields, where the locals still guard the valuable sap jealously.
Have you ever used frankincense in cooking?
No.
Perfumes, yes, but cooking, no.
We drink frankincense water.
'And after some persuasion, I managed to get a chance to capture my own frankincense.'
Literally, the sap appears instantly and within seconds of taking this first layer off.
So, can I taste the sap from this one?
Can I have a little taste?
Yeah, OK.
You can taste it.
It's bitter, eh?
Really bitter!
Exactly.
Yeah.
It was bitter, but at the same time, it was really complex.
It had a wonderful aromatic... fragrance to it.
A fruity note as well.
But more than anything else, I just found there was something...mystical about it.
I know what frankincense tastes like, but from being there, from that tree...
It gave me something I couldn't put your finger on...
Otherworldly.
Before I carried on in my search to find the next of my three gifts, there was time to share a special local drink - fresh camel's milk.
Camel milk.
OK, here.
It's good milk.
Good?
It's very good.
Now to the meal.
I decided to create a frankincense tea to include in my dish.
So this magical piece of kit is essentially a distillator.
Here, I have the frankincense sap, crystallised, that I brought back from Oman.
And the idea of this is to actually make an extraction - at a low temperature - of frankincense.
'This machine creates a vacuum which causes water to boil at 40 degrees.
'The vapour is then condensed to create a frankincense hydrosol.
'Extracting at low temperature means that much more of those magical qualities will be preserved.'
So this is my frankincense water.
With frankincense captured, next on my quest was myrrh.
For this, I headed to see some local healers who regularly use it as medicine.
When I arrived at their shop, I found it to be a treasure trove of exciting concoctions.
They call it the hand of mother Jesus, this one.
Is it?
It's like Viagra.
This is the best.
Class-A myrrh?
Yes.
You're looking at it and you think it looks a bit like a stone, but when you touch it and it's not, you can see it's crystallised sap.
'The purest myrrh comes straight from the trunk of a tree 'and is one of the most important local medicinal ingredients.
'It's used in all manner of ways, one of which is burning it to help sore throats.'
'It might be good for a cold, but it wasn't something I wanted to give my guests.
'The next option was myrrh mixed with honey.'
It's always better to eat after 24 hours.
'The honey mix was still too bitter to use in my meal.
'It tasted very much like rubber.
'How about eating myrrh in its rawest form?'
What would happen if I was just to bite a piece of myrrh?
It's quite bitter, but... that's only because I've just eaten it raw.
I'm thinking how on earth am I going to get this into the dish, because... unlike the frankincense, which was wonderfully aromatic and quite hedonistic... ..there was an aniseed-like quality about the myrrh, but there was also a real bitterness and a slight rubbery note to it.
That was going to be a real challenge.
'Back in the lab, I had to try and solve the problem of working the very medicinal myrrh into the dish.
'My hope was that in the time since we were in Oman, the myrrh oil and honey it had been mixed with 'might have mellowed its bitterness.'
Oh, God!
That is so bitter.
I wouldn't want that as a birthday present!
Getting the myrrh in is going to be a bit of a job.
'I still wanted all three of the Wise Men's gifts in my dish.
'I wasn't about to give up on myrrh yet.
'So I headed back to the source of the ingredient - the tree it comes from.'
I've got a feeling it's not, but there's only one way to find out.
I'm trying to make myrrh tea.
Just as I thought.
Absolutely useless!
Everything we did with it, it was bitter.
And then we found ourselves trying to work out how we can put myrrh in the dish and then disguise it.
And I thought, "Actually, what on earth's the point of doing this?"
It shouldn't be in there.
To make the dish delicious, we had to leave the myrrh out and bring it into the starter in a different form.
So I've come up with this.
It's a teaspoon, whittled from what we had left of the myrrh branch I brought back from Oman.
One of the key moments of any Nativity play is when the Wise Men bring their gifts to the newborn baby.
To give my guests a clue to the first course, hidden in their crackers, I gave them a small wafer that, when eaten, tasted just like the smell of a baby.
"A babe in a manger.
"Put it into your mouth and it melts magically."
Yeah.
And let it dissolve.
Under the tongue.
It's gone.
Mm!
I'm not going to call on your mother!
What is it?
It's Johnson's Baby Powder.
It's Johnson's talc.
While my guests puzzled, I needed to add the final element to my Three Wise Men dish - gold.
And my inspiration for that came from a visit to the Muscat marketplace in Oman.
The idea is that this is the third part of my triangle, I suppose - frankincense, myrrh and gold.
Obviously, as a chef, gold is not uncommon to use, but I just thought to be able to get it from the same place as, hopefully, I'll be getting frankincense and myrrh, it'll have that historical element and just make it more special.
Hand-hammered 21-carat gold, ready for use.
For making jewellery, that is.
Unfortunately, it's about 100 times too thick for me.
And the other slight complication... it's not edible.
Back in the lab, I needed to find a way to get gold into the dish.
This is 23-carat gold leaf for decorating food and beverages.
Gold fingers!
It's completely edible... and it's completely and utterly tasteless.
My idea was to use the gold leaf to wrap a stock cube and make a gold ingot, but to do that I first needed to make the stock.
This is a langoustine broth which has been reinforced with quite a large amount of onions, and cooked off in star anise, with a reduction of vermouth and other vegetables, aromatics and herbs.
And the reason for freezing it is because this next method, which is ice filtration, is just the most wonderful way to clarify a stock.
The frozen stock is wrapped in muslin and left for 24 hours.
What then happens is that the gelatine in the stock acts as a filter and as the stock thaws it holds behind its solids, giving an amazingly clear stock.
This is a great technique that can be used with all stocks containing gelatine.
The next stage for this is to freeze it in a minus-80 freezer.
Once the stock is frozen, I then move it to another piece of industrial equipment I own - a freeze drier - to remove all the moisture.
This needs to go in here for about a day-and-a-half.
This is the langoustine stock that has come out of the freeze drier.
You can see that it's taken on this amazing kind of honeycomb effect.
You've got to work very quickly because this will suck up moisture from the air.
I then need to push the dry stock into my gold bar mould.
So there it is.
That's my langoustine stock cube.
The next stage - I need to cover it in gold leaf.
And there is my gold bullion bar.
With all the gifts of the Three Wise Men finally included, it was time to turn my attention to the garnish for the dish.
I add egg yolk cooked with saffron to the plate.
Langoustine meat from the shells we used for the stock cube.
Next, a coffee and saffron bavarois.
Pistachios, lightly crystallised...
And tiny onions, lightly cooked and slightly pickled.
Then, to add a real perfume to the dish, sea urchin.
They have a wonderful violet character, which will work really well with the frankincense.
Finally, some tarragon tips and chervil leaf.
Not chopped, because that will destroy its delicate characteristic.
So, here's my first course - gold...frankincense...and myrrh.
So, take the gold ingot...
Ooh, smell the tea!
Place the gold ingot in the glass teapot.
Pour the frankincense tea over the ingot.
Stir.
It looks like a bouillon with pretensions.
Look at that.
That's lovely.
The leaf is coming off.
Stir.
I loved the luxury of the fact that out came this ingot of gold leaf, and then you poured a little sort of tea over it.
And the gold leaf floated into a million little pieces.
These were made in Oman.
I'm eating gold... and frankincense and myrrh.
Mm!
The taste of the broth is amazing.
And it's enhanced by the fact that we're eating gold leaf along with it.
It has very, very delicate and intense flavours.
It looks so pretty as well.
I hope it's not going to make our Christmas dinner at home look a bit shabby!
It's completely insanely, bonkersly, madly, Englishly...fantastic.
There are so many different tastes.
You can't make it at home, so you know that there's one person on the planet who is making it, and it's this mad inventor.
I tell you what, if I'd been served this when I was born, I'd have started a religion.
I had an uncle I was really fond of, and we used to go round to his house every Christmas and he had this wonderful red leather armchair and there was always a fire and he would smoke a pipe and have a glass of malt.
And it was just so Christmassy to me.
I wanted to try and somehow encapsulate all of that into this next course.
I had to try and get those amazing smells of whisky, leather and wood into my next dish, which I decided would be a palate-cleansing sorbet.
This is a leather extract.
You have to be careful with this one.
If it's too high, it's just like chewing a leather handbag.
Mm.
Not bad, that.
This is pipe tobacco.
MACHINE WHIRRS Can you see it?
So, it's sorbet...delicately licked...by pipe tobacco smoke.
'OK, so simply blowing smoke on to the sorbet wasn't going to work, but I wasn't giving up.'
We need to smell them.
I need it to be in the air.
I need to find a way of bringing the smell into the... serving of this dish, in such a way that it will really conjure up that memory.
What I needed was an expert in smell to help we capture those nostalgic aromas, and for that, I went to Paris and IFF - a leading perfumery where they create some of the world's best-known scents.
I'd come to meet Christophe Laudamiel, a kindred spirit of mine who is a genius with smell.
For Christmas, people have a lot of things with spices, cinnamon and orange, then mulberry, and cloves and laurel.
Cookies, gingerbread....
At Christmas time, it's freezing cold and there will be somebody there with chestnuts roasting.
And I always loved the smell.
For all of us, smell at Christmas time is hugely evocative.
The challenge for me was being able to create those natural smells in a magical way.
How many aroma molecules have you to work with?
Well, molecules, I would say around 1,000.
Very often you have 20, 50, 100.
This is very common in France - a formula with 50 ingredients, 100 ingredients, and people can't believe this.
They think we mix three or four things together.
Even nature is not like that - our own smell is 300 molecules.
So, having inspired Christophe, he set to work creating my smells.
He used all manner of techniques from an electric sniffing device that breaks down fragrances, to computer programmes that analyse every molecule.
But despite all the technology, the best instrument we had was still the nose.
So, the tobacco is stronger...
Yes, the leather is coming through.
And the leather comes through also.
This is a really nice balance.
Here, we are trying to recreate this nice tobacco feeling, and maybe a certain woody-ness.
The smell is a three-dimensional thing.
You breathe it, it surrounds you.
The hard-wiring that goes on with smell taps into memory and you can't control it.
You've just about got the whole smell of that wonderful old room.
The only thing I haven't got is the fire.
My idea was to get the fireplace into the meal by setting fire to the sorbet.
To do this, I'm going to add a special heat-resistant substance called gellan.
This will allow the sorbet to flame without melting.
To begin with, I add water to a pan.
Then to that, I add freeze-dried apple for a deep, appley flavour.
Apple juice, and this - malic acid.
Malic acid is the acid that is predominant in apples and it gives a really pleasing... sensation on the side of the tongue.
It generates saliva, which makes food mouth-watering.
And finally the magic ingredient - the gellan.
We just need to bring this to the boil, mixing while we do so.
I have to mix this as I heat it, to stop the gellan forming into a gel.
I then need to cool that down really quickly.
I'll just pop these containers into an ice bath.
After cooling, the mix is then churned in a sorbet machine.
I've churned this, but as with all sorbets and ice creams, it's very important to make sure you've got as small ice crystals as possible.
If they're too large, you'll detect them in the mouth and between the teeth and the ice cream will feel icy and not be as smooth as it should be.
Here I've got some whisky.
Time to check the mix.
So, there we are.
A flaming sorbet that really doesn't melt!
For serving this sorbet, first, take the bowl.
I've had this covered with leather.
The idea is when you're eating it, the touch is going to help the memory and the smell that we're going to be presenting with this dish.
Into that, I'm going to put the hot cast-iron casserole dish.
And this is what the sorbet is actually going to sit in.
Here I've got some cubes of apple that have just been macerated in an acidulated syrup.
And the sorbet will sit on top of the cubes.
So, here's the sorbet going into the pot.
It's now ready to go to my guests, so they can do the fun bit and set it on fire.
This is a leather plate.
A leather plate?!
Aha!
Now, you pour the whisky over.
You pour the Jack Daniels on to the sorbet - that went against all my instincts.
You light it...
And then you start tasting.
Delicious!
So, we've got our flaming sorbet - there's our fireplace - but where is the smell of the leather and where's the smell of the fire?
It's in the roses.
It's in the flower display on the table.
It was underneath the roses, underneath the vase - in the bigger container that it sat in, we put a bed of crushed dry ice.
Dry ice is wonderful at extracting aroma.
So Eric arrived at the table with a teapot that was full of hot water with the aroma that Christophe made - the smell of the room.
Wow!
That is fantastic.
Now, I can't see my spoon.
And you've got that intense wood smoke which always catches in your clothes.
What was lovely is you were sitting at the table and you could smell it.
Wow!
Ain't this wonderful?
The leather is warm, the cocotte is warm, and the sorbet is still freezing.
Yeah.
THEY LAUGH Wow!
It was fun.
That's the whole point about it.
Yes, the flavours were extraordinary and different and a combination the like of which you're not going to get anywhere else, but it was also fun.
Great fun.
I mean, you're setting fire to a sorbet!
Don't be ridiculous!
I knew I was going to use goose for the main course.
That's what I've had for the last ten years at Christmas.
But where were we going to get the goose from?
Goose, to me, is all about history, conjuring up images of Christmas past, so my first stop to find a goose was Hampton Court Palace, where they've been roasting the geese of kings and queens for centuries.
To understand more about this grand old bird, I met up with Marc Meltonville, who runs the Palace kitchens.
What is the history of roast goose in Britain?
As far as I can tell, it goes back so far we don't actually know.
It's one of those dishes linked with Christmas, but it goes back long before Christmas.
It seems that we ate geese at the harvest festival in pre-Roman times, and I couldn't work out why till I started reading into it.
Geese, along with leaves, fruits and everything, they disappear.
So the leaves fall off the trees, the light goes and the geese depart.
We know they migrate, but THEY didn't know where they went, and so they became part of the festival of death and rebirth.
This is ready now, is it?
I don't see why more people don't have this, instead of turkey, for Christmas.
No.
What's got me instantly is the amount of juice, not fat, but the amount of juice that's still in there.
It's nice.
It's delicious.
The long Christmas tradition and amazing taste that comes with goose was clear, but I was no closer to finding one for my meal.
We sourced four geese, all reared in different environments and on different feeds, in order to find my perfect bird.
You get that... like the fat from a grain-fed bird.
There's something fruity, almost, there.
For me, it's between these two.
One of the things that could be exciting is that if we feed the goose on a particular food, can that be tasted in the end result?
For me, the tastiest bird came from Essex and the farm of Simon Hughes, so that's where I headed.
Simon's been rearing birds on a diet of wheat and grass for years, and has his own unique way of calling the birds to dinner.
Come on, the geese!
Hey-hey-hey!
So they get fed now?
You've got the feed tubs here - what's in there?
That will be just wheat in those.
Are they feeding off the land here?
Yeah, they're eating the grass.
They eat a lot of stones and things out of the ground.
You see that it's full of holes.
I'm just looking at them eating that trailer!
"Oh, yes, I'll have a nice bit of undercarriage!"
I'd established that geese will eat almost everything, which is perfect for my plan.
The way meat tastes can be affected by the way in which the animal is fed.
I had an idea.
I was going to feed my geese the essence of Douglas fir pine, which I hoped would make them taste a little bit like Christmas tree.
Yeah.
They're gathering round, aren't they?
That's definitely the action when they eat a new food.
Oh, I think we're on to a winner there.
A success.
I think it's a definite success.
I'd found that the geese would eat the pine essence, which meant that I could control the way they tasted.
The next vital factor was catching myself a goose.
So what is the technique for picking these up, then?
So we're going to house them somewhere else.
We've made a little grotto.
'Animals that live in a peaceful and stress-free environment really do taste better.
'For the next two months, I wanted my geese to have the best life they could, 'so I built them their own special Christmas home.'
Oh, no!
Who built that thing?
How is that going to keep a goose in?
After a bit of a struggle, I finally got my geese into their new home.
'With the geese happy, I was off to make them some special feed 'that I hoped would make them taste really Christmassy.'
The idea is we've actually got the poultry feed.
That's 1.6kg and we want to try and get it mixed and stuck to these pine flakes, so we'll get a Christmas-tree flavour.
And some freeze-dried apple.
We've got some lucky geese here!
We need to eat this, because if it's good enough for us, it's good enough for a goose.
If it's not good enough for us, I ain't giving it to the geese.
'To the feed ingredients I also added the syrup, which, when heated, 'would hold it all together and make the first-ever three-Michelin-star goose feed.'
It's not too bad, is it?
Yes.
You get the pine, the apple comes through and the sage and onion definitely comes through.
In the background you get the wheaty note from the feed.
If my geese eat that mixture, they should then taste of apple and pine.
The one thing I hadn't realised was just how much they'd actually eat.
Almost 20 bags of feed.
To make all that, we needed to be working on a bigger scale.
So, here it is, our Christmas goose, fattened on a mixture of wheat and Christmas tree.
The idea is to use every part of the goose in the meal.
Nothing will go to waste.
The legs I take off, to cook in the traditional way, which I'll come to later.
Then the skin is removed, which I'll roast separately to get an amazing crispness.
Then the breast.
I'll vacuum-pack them in goose fat and cook them in a 56-degree water bath, which maintains all the moisture and flavour in the meat.
Now, back to the goose legs.
This recipe is called powdered goose and was popular in the 17th century.
I've cooked the goose legs very gently in goose fat for 50 hours at 65 degrees, and then smoked them for 20 minutes over cherry chips, giving them a delicate smoky flavour.
These will then be shredded and added to the veloute that I'm going to serve with the goose.
Now to my chestnut veloute.
I've brushed a bowl with hazelnut butter and coated it with ground hazelnuts.
And here I'm piping in some pureed potatoes... to the bottom of the bowl.
On top of that, I'm going to add some of the powdered goose.
These are the confit-ed goose legs that we smoked over cherry chips.
On top of that, I'm going to add...some pickled chestnuts ..and some white truffle.
Then finally, the chestnut veloute, a wonderfully rich mix made with chestnuts, butter and the stock from the goose.
To top it, I'll just put the cover on with some chestnuts on.
And it's missing the key thing.
This is based on chestnuts roasting on an open fire, so I need chestnuts roasted on an open fire.
I take a glass cloche and place it over some roasting chestnuts, into which the smoke then rises.
The idea of this is the guests, when they first take the soup, they pull the jar off and turn it upside down, then they'll get the full impact of the smell of chestnuts roasting on an open fire.
So, now to finish my goose main course.
First off, in here I've got some fresh black pudding.
This is cooked on a low temperature for a long time, continually mixing to get this wonderful, rich, velvety chocolate consistency.
I then carve the breasts into thick pieces, which I lightly glaze with a sauce made from wine, the goose bones and lots of spices.
Then I add some grelot onions.
Next, some small turnips cooked in a butter and water mixture.
Here is goose skin that we've... roasted and lacquered.
Now some salt that I've flavoured with the same pine that I fed to the geese.
Some sauce... a few drops of sage oil to mirror the stuffing we fed to the geese... then some pickling brine.
And finally, the goose cracker.
And there is my perfect Christmas goose.
Oh, yeah, look at that!
It brings me back it our house, the old Christmases around the electric fire.
(Wow!)
Don't eat the chestnuts.
The veloute is fantastic.
Oh, look at the veloute.
The veloute's amazing.
And it just became this fabulous taste.
There wasn't a word off that table.
There was just complete silence and six inveterate ego maniacs and "look at me, look at me" people just can't talk because they're eating!
Oh, that's lovely!
Oh, that is fantastic.
That is really, really up there for me.
It's one of the nicest things I've ever had.
God, it was really...
That is the sort of food that I'm going to go home and cry about in an hour's time.
That's lovely, isn't it?
That is gorgeous.
I absolutely love it.
This is just delicious.
The flavour...
It's just the intensity.
I've eaten in some of the best Little Chefs in the world, but this...
You've eaten some of the best little chefs?
Yes, but this is a step up.
I'll be honest.
It was - Sue felt the same - it's something I'll remember until I'm in my box.
Probably never to be repeated.
So far, we've got quite a few Christmas memories in this dinner.
But there's a key one that we're missing - Rudolph the red-nosed reindeer.
And to find Rudolph, we went to Siberia.
I braved minus-30 degree temperatures to visit northern Russia, because this is a place where reindeer are an integral part of the lives of the local people.
I arrived at a time of celebration.
It was the beginning of the reindeer season, a time of plenty for the local Evenk tribe which they mark by holding reindeer festivals.
Then, with my welcome over, it was time for the best bit of any festival, the eating and drinking.
Russian vodka.
Ruskan vodka.
THEY TOAST IN EVENKI 'Then, I had my first taste of Siberian reindeer.'
It is marrow bone, so it is the marrow from inside the bone.
It's delicious.
It's very rich.
Rich and fatty.
Next on the menu, reindeer kidney.
It's like an aphrodisiac.
I don't care if that's an aphrodisiac or not.
It tastes fantastic.
If it's an aphrodisiac, I don't want to be in here in a minute - she's eaten a whole raw kidney!
Needing to cool down a little, I headed back into the snow and found yet more reindeer concoctions.
Come and look over here.
Come.
Reindeer tea.
It's a kind of refined, upmarket Cup-A-Soup.
Then, with a skinful of vodka and a belly full of reindeer, it was time for a bit of a dance.
But I still had a worry.
These people live with reindeer, so they eat the reindeer, they wear the reindeer, the reindeer is their transport.
They love their animals.
They love the reindeer.
Their whole lives are intertwined with reindeer.
Well, that's not the case in Britain.
And I'm sorry, but I just couldn't bring myself to cook Santa's little helper.
It just didn't seem right.
I had to come up with another solution, so I headed to a reindeer farm.
On this farm, the reindeer are raised like cattle, but with temperatures reaching minus-60 at times, they're a little tougher than the average Friesian.
This particular farm had over 1,000 reindeer in their herd.
This is amazing.
We spent five hours getting here.
Talk about off the beaten track.
It was three hours on one road and, um... seeing this, it's all completely worth it.
Now the interesting thing I've learnt is the reindeers with the big antlers are the females.
The males are the ones predominantly without antlers.
The reindeer is completely intertwined with people's lives here.
It's what they live off.
I can't kill Santa's little helper for my Christmas lunch, but I do have an idea.
Reindeer milk!
MAN HOLDING REINDEER WHISTLES I can't see the teat.
There.
Well, I'm milking myself a reindeer!
I never thought I'd see the day.
It's so cold here, it's frozen, like the...
Perhaps I should pull the hair out first!
Mmm(!)
It's incredibly rich.
It's kind of...
It's just a really creamy cow's milk.
Apparently, frozen reindeer milk is quite a big thing around here and I can see why - it tastes delicious.
This might have just given me an idea.
I've got the milk.
Now all I've got to do is get home.
For me, at Christmas, the most exciting time of the day is breakfast, so...the idea is to use the reindeer milk and turn it into breakfast.
We're basing it on scrambled eggs on toast.
For the toast, I'm actually going to make some brioches, which is, essentially, really buttery bread.
But the difference with these is I've incorporated some mincemeat into the dough.
These need to go into the oven for about 45 minutes.
Now, to my reindeer milk.
I've decided to turn it into ice cream because of how great the frozen milk tasted in Siberia and to put it on top of my brioches.
To make this, I start by mixing egg yolks and unrefined castor sugar.
This has a slight molasses note, which adds a lovely complexity to the dish.
The eggs and sugar have been whisking for about five minutes, and now I need to heat some milk up.
Here I've got the reindeer milk.
This is very high fat, between 16% and 25%, which makes it incredibly rich, but I just need to temper that a little bit with some skimmed milk.
I heat the milk until it is hot, but not boiling and slowly add it to the mixture in the bowl, whisking the whole time.
Once that is incorporated... it goes back into the pan.
Once the mixture reaches 70 degrees, I hold it there for five minutes to pasteurise the mix.
The next stage is to cool this down as quickly as possible.
I'm going to plunge it into a bucket of ice.
So, here are the brioche loaves.
They've come out of the oven and I've left them to cool on a cake rack.
So when they are cold, I need to slice a couple of slices.
You can see the mincemeat running through the loaf.
Now, I've soaked the brioches in a mixture of egg, milk, cream, sugar, some walnut liqueur and some vanilla seeds.
What I'm making here is, in essence, posh eggy bread.
Put the brioches into the pan in which I have some sizzling clarified butter.
It's important to do two processes to this, the butter first then the caramel afterwards.
That way you get a wonderful crust that is also very delicate.
The idea is the bread slices will be soaked with this wonderful creamy mixture, so it'll be semi-liquid inside.
Once the slices are nicely golden, take them out of the pan and give the pan a quick clean with a dry cloth.
Then add some unrefined castor sugar.
I use this because it has low water content so it caramelises really quickly.
Take the brioche slices and pop them back in.
Be careful because this is very hot.
Add a little more sugar on top of the slices and turn them to get an even coating of the golden caramel.
Then drain your slices and put them on the plate.
So, the next step is to butter the toast.
I have got some brandy butter - a combination of butter, brandy and sugar.
In here, I'vegot some mincemeat which we made with a range of dried fruits and spices.
There is a bit of walnut in there as well.
Just a touch of that on the side.
So, there's the butter toast and the mincemeat and before I scramble the eggs, or scramble the ice cream, it wouldn't be breakfast without bacon, would it?
So over here I've got some crystallised bacon.
We've taken pancetta, frozen it, sliced it really thin - as thin as possible - and dried it in the oven so you get this wonderful, crisp, sweet bacon.
So, there's the bacon on toast.
I'm not scrambling them with heat.
I'm going to scramble them with this - liquid nitrogen.
The great thing about this technique is that because the nitrogen is minus 197-degrees centigrade, the ice crystals that form are tiny, making the ice cream really creamy and smooth.
There we are, one nitro-scrambled reindeer milk ice cream on toast.
Delicious.
We do breakfast.
And then we do lunch.
It's beautiful toast!
That's really good.
It?
This is amazing.
Oh, that's very...
It's so lovely.
It was like the nicest glass of milk you've ever drunk at just the right temperature from the fridge.
You know, when you have a chilled glass of milk that's just right.
Sugared bacon.
Wow!
It's extraordinary.
I don't understand how you can take... sugar and bacon and reconstitute them into a rasher that tastes that crispy and fatty, and yet...
Oh!
If you try to cook a brioche to get it that crisp and that soft in the middle...
How do you do that?
That's amazing.
This is just lovely.
But it was just delicious.
Obviously the fact that it came all the way from Siberia...
It doesn't land in your doorstep, ever.
So, again, it felt like you were eating a one-off special meal that you'd always remember.
That reindeer did not give up its milk in vain.
For me, talking about a perfect Christmas, it can't be a perfect Christmas without snow in some shape or form.
And...
I needed snow.
So the idea is I'm hiding behind a tree at the end of the meal and making it snow, creating snow for the end of my perfect Christmas dinner.
Which is exactly what I did.
It's snowing on Dara!
Ah!
Heston!
Wow!
I'm just excited to have eaten it, because you can see all the ideas going on and the boyish passion behind it.
He's taken the component parts of a great Christmas and spun something magical.
Truly astonishing!
It really has been one thing, after one remarkable thing, after another.
So it is very, very hard to take it all in.
I've just got vague memories of different textures and tastes and reactions of, "Oh, what's this?
Mmm!"
Brilliant.
That was wonderful.
It was absolutely magnificent.
Fantastic.
I do feel like I opened the back of something and there was a golden ticket in it and we got to have this.
This is insanely good.
Really, really good.
If somebody actually said to me, "How do you think it went?
I'd have to say that I think I've just cooked one of the most memorable meals of my life.
There's more to EastEnders this Christmas on BBC1.